Guide to the Harold Cruse Papers TAM.187
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Harold Cruse Papers
1940-2007
1970-2005
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Cruse, Harold
Kukic, Ivana
TAM.187
12.83 Linear Feet in 4 record cartons, 12 manuscript boxes, 4 half manuscript boxes, 1 flat box, and 7 folders in a shared oversized flat box.
Harold Cruse (1916-2005) was an author and professor best known for his monograph Crisis of the Negro Intellectual (1967), a Marxist-nationalist critique of the Communist movement and an endorsement of an autonomous revolutionary Black culture. Cruse was a professor at the University of Michigan at Ann Arbor and helped found their Center for Afro-American and African Studies (CAAS). The Harold Cruse Papers (1940-2007) consist of materials created and collected by Cruse. Materials include published and unpublished articles, as well as drafts of various written works; correspondence; ephemera and photographs; course syllabi, handwritten notes, conference materials, and lecture notes; and subject files and research materials.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions with the exception of box 22. Access to box 22 is restricted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Harold Cruse initially donated his papers to the Virginia Commonwealth University Special Collections and Archives in 1994. In 1995, the deed agreement between the two parties was mutually voided and the materials were returned to Dr. Cruse, who then donated them to Tamiment Library in 1996. The accession number associated with this gift is 1996.002. Additional materials were sent by Ivana Kukic in 2011. The accession number associated with these materials is 2011.104. Additional correspondence was found in the repository and added to the collection in 2014. The accession number associated with this material is 2014.045.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four series:
Series I: Correspondence, 1943-2005
Series II: Topical Files, 1941-2007
Series III: Writings, 1940-2005
Series IV: Personal Materials, 1943-2007
Folders are arranged alphabetically within each series, though some correspondence are also arranged chronologically.
Biographical Note
Harold Cruse (1916-2005) was an African American author and professor best known for his monograph Crisis of the Negro Intellectual (1967), a Marxist-nationalist critique of the Communist movement and an endorsement of an autonomous revolutionary Black culture.
Cruse was born in 1916 in Petersburg, Virginia and as a young child he moved to New York City with his father. After graduating high school and working a variety of jobs, Cruse served in World War II as a member of the 28th Quartermaster Regiment. He fought in North Africa and Italy.
Harold Cruse joined the Communist Party in 1947 and remained a member for seven years. During his time with the Communist Party, he contributed drama and literature reviews to its newspaper, the Daily Worker. He also attended the Communist Party's George Washington Carver School in Harlem. Cruse wrote four plays during the 1950s, but none were produced. Thereafter, he concentrated on nonfiction. In the late 1960s, Cruse joined the faculty of the University of Michigan at Ann Arbor and helped found their Center for Afro-American and African Studies (CAAS).
Cruse's other books include Rebellion or Revolution? (1968), Plural but Equal (1987), and The Essential Harold Cruse: A Reader (2002).
Scope and Content Note
The Harold Cruse Papers (1940-2007) consist of materials created and collected by Harold Cruse. The collection contains correspondence from individuals including John Conyers, Langston Hughes, Manning Marable, Mara Julius, and Wole Soyinka. It also contains correspondence from book publishers, Cruse's literary agent, and academic institutions.
Harold Cruse's interest in revolutionary Black culture and the Civil Rights movement is represented throughout the collection in the form of Freedom Now Party materials; correspondence with author, Civil Rights activist, and former president of the Monroe, North Carolina chapter of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People (NAACP), Robert F. Williams; correspondence related to the Eldridge Cleaver Legal Defense Fund, an organization established in 1976 designed to provide financial assistance to Black Panther Party leader Eldrige Cleaver for his ongoing legal expenses; and research materials related to African American and Civil Rights history.
The collection also contains published and unpublished copies of Harold Cruse's articles; drafts of his various written works; copies of plays and musicals written by Cruse; articles about Harold Cruse and obituaries; handwritten notes; course syllabi, and lecture notes; research materials, subject files, and conference materials; and copies of his manuscript, the Crisis of the Negro Intellectual.
Personal materials related to Cruse's life outside of academia can also be found within this collection. These items consist of a scrapbook and documents relating to his military service during World War II; photographs of Cruse's travels, portraits of himself, and photographs of his family; some of his undergraduate coursework focused on film studies; address books and contact lists; and copies of his curriculum vitae.
Communists -- United States.; Reviews (document genre); African Americans -- Civil rights; African American communists; Marxist criticism.; African American journalists; African American authors; Printed ephemera.; Correspondence.; Lecture notes.; Manuscripts for publication.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.; World War, 1939-1945.; Obituaries.; Colloquia and conference papers; Reed, Adolph L., 1947-; Soyinka, Wole; Diop, Cheikh Anta; Conyers, John, 1929-; Marable, Manning, 1950-2011; Gorney, Jay, 1896-1990; Kukic, Ivana; Julius, Mara, 1930-2011; Cruse, Harold; University of Michigan; Williams, Robert F. (Robert Franklin), 1925-1996; Cleaver, Eldridge, 1935-1998
- Series I. Correspondence, 1943-2005; 2.6 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons and 1 manuscript box
  Scope and Contents
  Notable correspondents found in this series include John Conyers, Cheikh Anta Diop, Jay Gorney, Langston Hughes, Manning Marable, Adolph Reed Jr., and Wole Soyinka. There is also one file of World War II-era letters to Cruse, and several thick files of academic correspondence. This series also contains correspondence from Mara Julius, Harold Cruse's partner of 36 years.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 22 is restricted.
  - Subseries A: Alphabetical
    - Academic, undated, 1969-1990 (Box 1, Folder 1-4)
    - Afro-American Historic Association Niagara Frontier, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Afro-American Realty Corporation, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - American Library Association, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - American Security Council, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Antioch College, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Association of African Historians, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Bahai National Information Office, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bergman Publishers, 1969-1970 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Black Books Bulletin, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Booker, Sue, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Character Studies Productions, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Claudia Menza Literary Agency, 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Condolences for Harold Cruse's Death, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Congress on Research and Dance, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Conyers, John Jr. - Congressman, 1974-1979 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Cook, William (Talking Drum Cable Television Program), 1986, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Diggs, Charles C. Jr., Congressman, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Diop, Cheikh Anta, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Diop, M Alioune, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Greene, Vera, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Fabre, Genevieve, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Fitchue, Leah Gaskin, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Fontenat, Chester, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Fulton, Richard (Lecture Agent), 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Gorney, Jay, 1950, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Handwritten (Miscellaneous), 1968-1988 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Hare, Nathan, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Harper Collins Publishers, 2000, 2003 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Haynes, Eugene - Musician, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Higginson, John E., 1988 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Howard University, 1976-1980 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Hughes, Langston, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Institute for Historical Review, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Institute for People Enterprises, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Johnson, Cliff - Black Americans International Intercultural Organization, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Johnson, Paul Kwame, 2004 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Jones, Mack - Prairie View University, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Julius, Mara, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Liberation Magazine, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Locke, Rovan G, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Marable, Manning, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - McClusky, John - Indiana University Press, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Moore, Carlos, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Negro History, Conference On, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - New York Times, 1968-1979 (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Norman, Fred, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Reed, Adolph Jr., 1986 (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Schmeri, Rudi, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Socialist Scholars Conference, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Soyinka, Wole, 1975-1976 (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - RESTRICTED: SUNY - David Nielson Tenure Review, 1977 (Box 22, Folder 1)
      This folder is restricted to researchers.
    - Story, Ralph, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Taylor, Clyde, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Thorpe, Earl E., 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Vandenberg, Vicki and Ed, 1969 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Wacker, Fred, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Walter, Ronald, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Walton, Haynes, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 55)
    - Washington, University of, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Weitz, Marvin, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - William Monroe Trotter Institute, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - William Morris Agency, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - William Morrow and Company Publishers, 1965-1976 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Wynter, Sylvia, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - World War II-era Letters to Cruse, 1943-1947 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Subseries B. Chronological
    - Correspondence, 1952-1957 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Correspondence, 1962-1993 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Correspondence, 1971, 1974, 1978-1984, 1999-2005 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
- Series II. Topical Files, 1941-2007; 5.25 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons, 4 manuscript boxes, and 1 oversized box
  This series contains ephemera, lecture notes, subject files, course syllabi, conference materials, research notes, research materials, and some correspondence relating to Cruse's activity as a public intellectual. This series also includes files on the Eldridge Cleaver Legal Defense Fund and on Robert Williams.
  The file "African American and Civil Rights History -- Lynching Photograph" contains a graphic photograph depicting the death of an African American male murdered by the Klu Klux Klan in the 1980s.
  - Affirmative Action and Racism, 2001 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - African American and Civil Rights History, 2000-2004 (Box 6, Folder 11-12)
  - African American and Civil Rights History -- Lynching Photograph, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - African American Museum, 1977-1987 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - African Diaspora, 2000-2001 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - African World, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - African World Festival, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - AfroAmerican Communicator, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Afro Arts Theater, 1955, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - American Festival of Negro Arts (AFNA), circa 1965-1968, undated (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - American Negro Arts Festival, 1943-1994 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - American Society of African Culture - "The Negro Writer and his Relationship to his Roots", 1959 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Antioch College, 1982 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - AMSAC (American Society for African Culture) Writers Conference - Notes, ca. late 1950s (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Association of American University Presses, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Association for the Study of Afro American Life and History, 1976-1988 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Banfield, William, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Black American Music Symposium (Cruse's Notes as Moderator), 1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Black Internationalism: Embracing an Economic Paradigm (Brown, Jeffrey M.), 2002 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Black Law Students Alliance - Discussion Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Black Party: Founding Convention, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Black Scholar, 1969-1989 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Blacks in Predominantly White Colleges and Universities, The First National Think Tank On, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Bubbling Brown Sugar, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - California State University, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Carleton College, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Castle, Irene, undated (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Caucus of Black Sociologists (Includes Lecture Notes), 1975 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Center for Afro American and African Studies, 1981-1986 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Center for Soviet and East Europe Studies, 1976-1986 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Citizens for Community Development, 1978, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Clash of Civilizations, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Cleveland State - Drimmer, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Conference Materials, 1973-2000 (Box 7, Folder 6-8, Box Shared Tamiment 174, Folder 8)
  - Contract for Article on "Key Issues in the Afro-American Experience - Part Two", 1969 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Cleaver, Eldridge (Legal Defense Fund, Other), 1969-1981 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Cornell University, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Course Outlines - Afro American Studies (Course 201 and 202), ca.1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Declaration of Black Intellectuals and Scholars in Support of the People's Struggle of West Papua New Guinea and East Timor Against Indonesian Colonialism, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Dvorak, Anton, 2003-2004 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Ecole des Hautes Etudes en Sciences Sociales, 1980 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Freedom Now Party - Harlem, circa 1961-1963 (Box 7, Folder 11, Box 8, Folder 1, Box Shared Tamiment 174, Folder 9)
  - Garvey, Marcus, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Harvard University - Alain Locke Symposium, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Harvard University - William Seymour Society Lectures, 1982-1985 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - History 572 - Course Description, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Independent Citizens Committee for the Development of Harlem and the Harlem Neighborhoods Association, Inc., 1965-1966 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Indiana, University of (re: Promotion of Herman Hudson, and Minority Studies Program, 1977-1978 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Institute for People Enterprises (Conference on Urban Choices for Survival), 1979 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Institute of Scientific Information, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - In these Times, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - International Association for Cultural Freedom, 1971, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Iowa, University of - Lecture (re: Paul Robeson), 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Jazz, 2003 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Jefferson School of Social Science - Marxism and the Negro Question, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Johnson, Cedric, 2007 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Macalester College - Hubert Humphrey Lecture Notes, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Moore, Steven, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Morgan State University Lecture (Includes Notes), 1975-1978 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - "Moynihan Report, A Statement on the", undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - National Coalition of Blacks for Reparations in America (N'COBRA), 2000 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - National Conference for Arists -- International Conference Medal, 1985 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - National Conference of Artists - Lecture: Black Art in the 1930's, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - National Endowment for the Humanities - American Culture Panel, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - National Urban League, 1975-1978 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Neel, Alice, 1974 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - New Dimensions, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - News of the Emeriti - Harold Cruse, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Olive Harvey College - Speech, 1977-1988 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Owens, Leslie - The Dismissal of, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Pennsylvania, University of, 1986-1988 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Postcards of African Americans, undated (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Princeton University, 1976, 1989 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Reparations, 2000 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Sacramento Working Conference on the Black Political Party, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - "Separate but Equal" - International Institute of Flint (Lecture Notes), 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Stanford University Speech, 1994 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Studies on the Left, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - SUNY Brockport - African and Afro-American Studies Department, 1991 (Box Shared Tamiment 174, Folder 10)
  - United Negro and Allied Veterans of America - New York State Council, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - University of Michigan, 1984-1985 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - University of Michigan -- Center for AfroAmerican and African Studies (CAAS), 2006-2007 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - University of Michigan -- Center for Afro-American and African Studies (CAAS) -- 35th Anniversary Conference in Honor of Harold Cruse, 2006 (Box 9, Folder 1, Box Shared Tamiment 174, Folder 11)
  - University of Michigan -- Center for Afro-American and African Studies (CAAS) -- Porgy and Bess Project, 1991 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Commonwealth University, 1989-1990 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Wayne State University Humanities Conference, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Williams, Robert F., 1961-1986 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Series III: Writings, 1940-2005; 8.02 Linear Feet in 2 record cartons, 2 half manuscript boxes, 7 manuscript boxes, 1 flat box, and 1 oversized flat box
  This series contains published and unpublished articles, as well as drafts of various written works; copies of plays and musicals written by Cruse; book and theater reviews; essays about Harold Cruse and copies of his obituaries; and an almost complete typescript of the Crisis of the Negro Intellectual.
  - "Aesthetic Theory of American Negritude", undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Afro American Communicator, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - "An Afro-American's Cultural Views", undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Afro American Youth Cultural Conference, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - "American Negritude", undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - "American Negritude" - Exploratory Philosophical Notes - Part II, undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - "The American Negro and the Cuban Revolution", undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - "The American Negro Manifesto on Cultural Revolution", undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Articles about Harold Cruse, 1997-2005 (Box 9, Folder 4-5, Box Shared Tamiment 174, Folder 12)
  - Articles about Harold Cruse -- Obituaries, 2005 (Box 9, Folder 6, Box Shared Tamiment 174, Folder 14)
  - Article on: Negro in the Theater, 1951 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - "Assimilation in American Life" (Review by Cruse), 1964 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Avant-Propos (Essay in French), undated (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Baldwin, James - Articles About, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - "Battle of Montreal" - African Heritage Studies Association, undated (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - "Behind the Black Power Movement", undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - "Black Anti-Semitism", undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - "Black Anti-Semitism" - Notes on, 1985-1986 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - "Black Bourgeois", undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - "The Black Political Process - Myth or Reality - A Theoretical Analysis", 1978 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - "Black Intellectuals and Others - A Critical Survey" (Draft), undated (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Black Intellectuals and the Racial Divide, undated (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
  - The Blacks and the Idea of Revolution, undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - The Blacks and the Red, 1995 (Box 10, Folder 4-5)
  - "Black Studies: Interpretation, Methodology, and the Relationship to Social Movements", 1971 (Box 3, Folder 30, Box 10, Folder 6)
  - "Bohemia Revisited", undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Book Review by Cruse of Freedom Song: A Personal Story of the 1960's Civil Rights Movement, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Book Review by Cruse of Introduction to Black Studies, by Maulana Karenga, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Book Reviews by Cruse (Various), 1950-1964 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - "The Changing Face" (Drafts), 1994 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - "Charles Riley and New Negro Renaissance", undated (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - "A Chess Manual for the 'Potzers' by the Master Monsieur Fred Duval" - As Told by Cruse, ca. late 1950s-early 1960s (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Cleaver, Eldridge: The Fire this Time? (Review of) by Cruse, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - "Contemporary Dialectics", ca.1963 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - The Creative and Performing Arts and the Afro-American Struggle for Identity and Credibility, 1974 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - "The Creative and Performing Arts and the Struggle for Identity and Credibility", undated (Box 3, Folder 39, Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Crisis of the Negro Intellectual, undated (Box 3, Folder 40-43, Box 19)
  - Crisis of the Negro Intellectual - "Black Nationalism and American Socialism" (by Eugene Genovese), 1968 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Crisis of the Negro Intellectual - Critique (by Bob Higgins), 1978 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Crisis of the Negro Intellectual -- Drafts, undated (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
  - Crisis of the Negro Intellectual - Twentieth Anniversary, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Crisis of the Negro Intellectual -- Xerox Copy, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - "Cuba, Marxism, Nationalism, and the American Negro", undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "Cuba and the North American Negro", undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - "Cuba and the North American Negro: A Study in Two Revolutionary Perspectives", undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "Culture and the Negro Question" - Review by Cruse, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - "Cultural Identity and the Afro American", undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "Cuba, Marxism, Nationalism, and the Afro-America", undated (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - "Death of White Sociology, Outline for", 1975 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "The Delta Rose", undated (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Destiny of the Black Elites, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Destiny of the Black Elites -- Handwritten Draft, undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Destiny of the Black Elites and Black Intellectuals and Others (Drafts), undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Dialects of Race and Culture: The Collected Essays of Harold Cruse, undated (Box 12, Folder 2-3)
  - Dispatches from the Ebony Tower (Draft), 1999 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Drafts of Essays, undated (Box 12, Folder 5-7, Box 13, Folder 1-3)
  - "The Economics of Black Nationalism", undated (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - "The Education of a Rebel", undated (Box 4, Folder 8-8I)
  - "The Fire This Time?", 2003 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - "Force and Violence: from Monroe to Watts", undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - "From Shibe Park to Yankee Stadium", undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - "George Capdeville's Ancestry", undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - "Green Pastures: Twenty Years Ago and Today", 1951 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Handwritten Notes, undated (Box 13, Folder 7-8, Box 14, Folder 1)
  - "Harold W. Cruse: The Man and His Works - A Selected Bibliography" (JoAnn Hall), undated (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - "The Historical Roots of American Social Change", 1971 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - "Historical Roots of Social Change and Social Theory", undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - "Historical Roots of Social Change and Social Theory" (Handwritten), undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - "The House He Once Lived in", 1950 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - "The House He Used to Live in", 1949 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - "The Intellectuals and Force and Violence", undated (Box 4, Folder 17)